have you ever wondered how it is that a
global economic system was put in place
that is so antithetical to human
wellbeing well I'd like to share with
you a story that is historically valid
and factual that explains how it is that
a theory of human nature it has
completely ungrounded in science it's
actually in direct contradiction to
science I has come to be the dominant
paradigm for economic activity in the
world today now this theory that I'm not
alluding to is called the theory of
rational action it's sometimes also
called rational choice theory or the
rational actor model and essentially it
says that the foundation of human nature
is that we are self-interest maximizers
you can almost think of us as being like
robots that calculate our best interest
for every decision where we take on one
hand the positive things that will come
out of a decision and on the other hand
the negative things what are called the
costs I and are the benefits and the
costs and then we weigh them against
each other and somehow we come up with a
solution that is going to maximize our
utility or in other words give us the
best ratio of positive to negative in
the decision now it turns out that this
theory was not developed by behavioral
scientists in fact it came from the RAND
Corporation in the 1940s and 1950s and
it was not developed by psychologists
instead it was developed by
mathematicians and strategists and it's
helpful to have a little bit of context
that the RAND Corporation which is a
non-profit think tank set up in
California was actually put in place by
the Air Force after World War two they
the Air Force had gotten a lot of very
lucrative defense contracts during World
War two to build aircraft and ships to
take aircraft out to sea and bombs for
the aircraft and so on and they wanted
to have a neutral body or an
organization that appeared to be neutral
that could advocate on their behalf for
large defense spending to the Air Force
in competition with the army of the Navy
in the Marines and so they set up the
RAND Corporation to try to secure
contracts for the Air Force and one of
the things that came about after World
War two ended was the rise of the Cold
War in this conflict between or this
economic competition between the Soviet
Union on one hand in the United States
and Western Allies on the other and a
group of mathematicians were hired by
the rand corporation to explore ways
that the Air Force could benefit from
this emerging tension between these two
players and they came up with what is
now known as game theory basically a
group of mathematicians came together
and export strategies and they created
games or call them rules for interaction
that let them create scenarios and run
them and test them and these scenarios
were based on assumptions about human
nature so rational choice theory or the
theory of rational action was developed
as part of these game theories being
developed by mathematicians at the RAND
Corporation in partnership with other
places but really it was the nexus for
all that work and one of those games
rather crudely was called fuck you buddy
now we know it as the prisoner's dilemma
and it was a scenario where there were
two actors competing with each other
where each of them had incomplete
information about the other and they had
to decide whether they were cooperate or
whether they would not cooperate and the
mathematical solution that was given the
best outcome was to basically to lie to
pretend that one was going to cooperate
with their opponent and then cheat them
at the last minute to screw them over so
that they maintained the best possible
situation where they would not give
anything to the other person but they
might trick the other person into giving
something to them which was considered
to be the best outcome interestingly the
first time that an experiment was run
with real human beings to see whether
this road
tional action process what actually be
would play out the RAND Corporation was
run primarily by researchers who were
men and this was during a time when
there was a widespread prejudice that
treated women as though they were not
rational and men were so um they did
this study where they had the
secretaries in their office do this
prisoner's dilemma game and all the
women in the office violated the rules
of the game and cooperated with each
other sharing information and working
out on what's now called tit for tat or
the reciprocity strategy where I help
you you help me and rather than having
this invalidate the theory the
researchers in their prejudice just said
well women are irrational so of course
they don't follow the rules of rational
action but that doesn't invalidate our
theory it just confirms it well in
hindsight we conceded this actually only
confirms the bias of the researchers but
what's interesting is that the theory of
rational action was then taken over the
next 40 to 50 years to build an entire
global economic system based on it which
is laissez-faire economics it's also
called neoclassical economics I the sad
thing is that behavioral scientists
didn't start questioning the assumptions
of rational choice theory for several
decades actually not until the mid-1970s
when a research project was undertaken
led by researchers like Daniel Kahneman
Amos Tversky Paul slovic and others and
they set out to to question you know to
really to do experimental studies to see
if the assumptions of rational choice
they were valid and interestingly the
very first experiments conducted by
behavioral scientists not only did they
not support rational choice theory but
they contradicted it and invalidated in
really profound ways one specific way
that they did that just to give you a
sense is that the mathematics of
rational choice theory requires that
preferences remain constant across time
it's what's in mathematics is called the
noncommutative requirement that a plus B
must always equal B plus a but if a and
B change value or reverse order then a
plus B does not equal
does not equate to people say in the
same way and so on the first experiments
by psychologists showed that you could
reverse people's preferences by changing
the way that you frame the question so
you frame the question in one way and
you get people to come out with option a
is better than option B and you frame in
a different way that's logically
equivalent but has a different emotional
tone to it and you would get people to
change their preference and say they
prefer be over a so the long and short
of it is that when behavioral scientists
started studying the questions the
assumptions rather underlying rational
choice theory they immediately
invalidated it and actually the first
psychologist currently the only
psychologist to get a Nobel Prize in
Economics was Daniel Kahneman for this
work so it's helpful to to ask ourselves
this question if we have assumptions
about human nature that go into the
design of our global institutions all
the way to the level of the emergent
global economy and those assumptions are
based on philosophical ideas that are
not grounded in fact and in an actuality
contradict how real human nature works
then we've got a conundrum and so what
we need to do to remedy that kind of
problem is to have what two cognitive
scientists George leg off and Mark
Johnson call empirically responsible
philosophy which is that you use
empirical methods like the scientific
studies done by psychologists in the 70s
to question the assumptions of your
philosophy before you implement them so
that you can improve upon your own
internal ideological biases so this is
just a quick example of how the story of
the rise of rational choice theory
should cause us to take caution and be
more systematic and rigorous than the
methods that we use to determine how we
develop our theories of human nature and
another lesson that we can take away
from this is that the cognitive and
behavioral sciences studies in
psychology and neuroscience and
linguistics and other fields can help
guide our theory building in philosophy
as well so it actually goes both ways so
there you have it that's the story of
the
rise of rational choice theory and how
it was establishing a set of
presumptions about human nature that
were later invalidated by cognitive
science and so now as we move forward
and we ask ourselves how do we build a
global economy that works for human
beings we'd better be sure to take the
sciences of human nature that are
telling us how human beings actually
work into consideration as part of our
design process thank you and I hope this
is useful for you